Guide to the Walter Schuetrum Papers ALBA.136
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Walter Schuetrum Papers
1937-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Schuetrum, Walter.
ALBA.136
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Walter J. Schuetrum (1911-1986), a native of Wisconsin, served as an ambulance driver in the Spanish Civil War. After serving in the front lines of some of the crucial battles of the War, he retunred to the U.S. and, after service in World War II, settled in San Francisco. He worked as a longshoreman and a merchant seaman and was active in the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, the National Maritime Union, and the Bay Area Post of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. This collection of his papers includes documents, correspondence, ephemera, and artifacts from his time in Spain, as well as correspondence and papers from the 1960s-1980s.
Provenance
The Walter Schuetrum Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Nancy Fontana in 1996. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Separated Materials
Photographs from the Walter Schuetrum Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Missing Title
I. Spanish Civil War Files. 1937-1939
II. General Files, Post-Spanish Civil War, 1946-1987
III. Artifacts and Memorabilia, 1937, undated.
The collection is organized in 3 series. Files are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Walter J. Schuetrum was born in Superior, Wisconsin on October 18, 1911. The son of a German-American miner turned switchman for the Great Northern Railroad who was an avid trade-unionist, Schuetrum early in his life developed a concern for political and labor issues. In 1937 he volunteered for service with the Loyalist forces in Spain. In Spain he became an ambulance driver, and was present at many of the War’s crucial battles. In the aftermath of the Battle of Teruel he was reported deceased, misinformation that was publicized in Wisconsin Newspapers and only corrected after he wrote a letter to his family assuring them of his safety.
After the Spanish Civil War, Schuetrum returned to Wisconsin with his close friend and fellow veteran Randall "Petet" Smith and soon after moved with his wife, Viola Gruenhagen Schuetrum, to San Francisco. On the West Coast, he got a job as a longshoreman and became an active member and organizer for the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union. During World War II, Schuetrum joined the U.S. Army, but because of his involvement in the Spanish Civil War, was barred from fighting overseas and instead worked as an instructor on land ships at the Indiantown Gap Military Reservation in Pennsylvania. He was discharged in 1946, and went on to get his seaman's papers and work work on merchant ships in the Pacific, where he organized for the National Maritime Union.
In 1961, Schuetrum, along with other veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the Medical Service, was invited to the German Democratic Republic and spent three months there. In the same year, with other veterans who were on that trip (including nurse Sana Goldblatt and Steve Troxell), Schuetrum helped to establish the Bay Area Post of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). Although he never held an administrative position in VALB, he was nonetheless directly involved in many of its activities and proceedings. He returned to East Germany three times in the 1970s and traveled to Spain with other U.S. veterans in 1982. He died in 1986.
Sources: Fontana, Nancy. “Walter Schuetrum, My Father”. The Volunteer Vol. III, 2 (Oct. 1986)
Scope and Content note
The collection is separated into three series.
Series I. Spanish Civil War Files, 1937-1939 consists of material from 1937-1939, from Schuetrum’s time in Spain and immediately following. Included are letters from him to his family and friends, documents pertaining to his membership in the IB and various other Spanish organizations, and ephemera collected during his tour.
Series II. General Files, 1946-1987 consists of all materials that postdate the Spanish Civil War. Included are documents pertaining to Schuetrum’s enlistment in the Army, his membership in the I.L.W.U, and correspondence from friends and other veterans. Much of the material dated after 1970 is V.A.L.B. related.
Series III. Artifacts and Memorabilia consists of non-print memorabilia from Spain.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Madrid (Spain); Barcelona (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Foreign public opinion.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Causes.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Teruel, Battle of, Teruel, Spain, 1937-1938.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Biography files.; Correspondence.; Jarama River Valley (Spain); Personal papers.; Belchite (Spain) -- History -- Siege, 1937.; Memorabilia.; Printed ephemera.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Smith, Randall, 1917-1989; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV -- |v Biography; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Martin, Fredericka I.
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Files, 1937-1939., 1 box
  - Ambulance Drivers Handbook (Comisión Reguladora de Carreteras), [1937] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Asociacion de Amigos de la Union Sovetica: Stamps, Membership cards, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boarding Receipts, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carnet Militar (signed by Langston Hughes, Paul Robeson, John Strachey, and James Waterman Wise), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Map from The Evening Telegram (Superior, WI), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: On War, in English and French (l’Humanité), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: WS Service in Spain and Return Home in Superior, WI Newspapers, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Communist Party of Spain: Carnet de Afiliado (Membership Card), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Communist Party of Spain: Farewell Card to International Brigade Volunteers, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - “Conquests of the Salvadorean Army of Spain” (Map), [1938] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: “A Letter from Spain,” by WS (reprint from an unidentified periodical, 2 copies), Oct 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Bard, Sam (Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade) to Mrs. Schuetrum, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Buckley, Nat T., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Dorfs, Sylvia, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Harju, Rudolph, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: “International Comrades” to Mrs. Schuetrum (Thank You Letter for Package of Sweets), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Kartinen, Signe, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: McCollough, Kenneth, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Parents, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Smith, Violet to Mr. and Mrs. W.J. Schuetrum, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Sundstrum, Lawrence H./ Boehme, Fred N., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Arrival Notification for WS, Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hand-Drawn Map of Ebro Region/ “List of the Personnel of Villa”, [1937] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Log of Vessels: S.S. President Roosevelt, Cunard White Star R.M.S. Ausonia, 1937; 1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mackenzie, David: “Report on the War in Spain” at Odd Fellows Hall (Flyer), [1937] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mailing Receipts, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notebook of Volunteers’ U.S. Addresses and List of New York City Restaurants, [1938-1939] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Notes on History of Conflict and Personal Experiences in Spain, for Unidentified Project, [1939] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notes (Typed): “Why Walter Went to Spain,” w/ Extracts from his Letters (Author Unidentified), [1930s] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Pamphlets (Includes Map of Paris for 1937 Exposition and “Guerra Viva” by José Herrera Petere), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Radio Interview with WS on WEBC (Transcript), [1939] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Reconquista, 35 División (Periodical), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Registration Form (American Consular Services), [1937] (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Relatives of American Prisoners in Franco Spain: “Release Americans in Franco Prisons” (Petition), [1939] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Republican Stamps and Currency (“Vales”), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - El Socors Roig de Catalunya: Card to International Brigades Volunteers, [1938] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Song-Cards: “Al Soldado Internacional Caído en España” (To a Fallen International Soldier), “A Jaskel Honigstein”, “Lina Odena”, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Speech on War Experience, [1939] (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 35 División del Ejército Popular: Carnet de Honor, [1938] (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Transport Documents (Safe-Conducts, Hoje de Ruta, etc.), 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Unión Nacional de Estudiantes de España: Honorary Membership Card, [1937-1938] (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series II: General Files (Post-Spanish Civil War), 1946-1987., 2 box
  - Abramson, Sam, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Black-Jewish Relations, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Barr, Reuven, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bender, Ed, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Berch, Victor, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bach, Ejgil, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 6)
  - Cesarini, Juan Carlos, 1982 (Box-folder 2, Folder 7)
  - Dahlem, Franz and Reuter, Fritz, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 8)
  - Delaney, Gerry, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 9)
  - DeMaio, Tony, 1982; 1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 10)
  - Durmayer, Heinrich, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 11)
  - El Salvador: Bay Area Protests, [1984] (Box-folder 2, Folder 12)
  - Eriksson, Per, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 13)
  - Farmer-Labor Progressive Federation: Campaign Ad for WS Board of Education Run, undated (Box-folder 2, Folder 14)
  - Feinberg, Helen Freeman, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 15)
  - Felsen, Milt, 1986 (Box-folder 2, Folder 16)
  - Fishman, Moe, 1961-1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 17)
  - Forance, Priscilla, 1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 18)
  - Funke, Otto, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 19)
  - G., Susan (re: Swedish International Brigades Monument, “La Mano”), 1981 (Box-folder 2, Folder 20)
  - Geiser, Carl, 1970-1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 21)
  - German Democratic Republic: I.B. Commemorations, Trips etc., 1961-1981 (Box-folder 2, Folder 22)
  - Germany: Anti-Fascist Rally (Berlin), Clippings, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 23)
  - Germany: Charles R. Allen, “A Letter from East Germany”, 1982 (Box-folder 2, Folder 24)
  - Germany: Democratic German Report (News Letter), 1975 (Box-folder 2, Folder 25)
  - Goldblatt, Sana, undated (Box-folder 2, Folder 26)
  - Gonzalez, Celestino, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 27)
  - Graeber, Kenneth, 1970 (Box-folder 2, Folder 28)
  - Green, Nan, 1977; 1979 (Box-folder 2, Folder 29)
  - Greeting Cards (German), 1978; 1984 (Box-folder 2, Folder 30)
  - Harju, W. A., 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 31)
  - Hartzman, Jack, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 32)
  - Hill, Josephine, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 33)
  - Iceland, Ben, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 34)
  - Identification Cards (Includes Honorable Discharge Card), 1957-1964 (Box-folder 2, Folder 35)
  - International Longshoremen’s and Warehousemen’s Union, Local 10: Dues Card, 1946-1955 (Box-folder 2, Folder 36)
  - Italy: 40th Anniversary, International Brigades (Florence), 1976 (Box-folder 2, Folder 37)
  - Italy: VALB Meeting with Sergio Segre, 1976 (Box-folder 2, Folder 38)
  - Johnson, John and Irma, 1976 (Box-folder 2, Folder 39)
  - Karsten, Peter, 1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 40)
  - Klaster, Leo, 1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 41)
  - Klebba, Gunter, 1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 42)
  - Knudsen, Arne, 1983 (Box-folder 2, Folder 43)
  - Kozar, Tom, 1979 (Box-folder 2, Folder 44)
  - Kramer, Jacob, [1986] (Box-folder 2, Folder 45)
  - Krauss, Martin, 1980 (Box-folder 2, Folder 46)
  - Kummerer, Martha, 1977; 1978 (Box-folder 2, Folder 47)
  - Landis, Art, 1976; 1981 (Box-folder 2, Folder 48)
  - Lending, Edward, 1981 (Box-folder 2, Folder 49)
  - Macfarlane, John, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 50)
  - Maki, Martin, 1973; 1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 51)
  - Map to Schuetrum Home, undated (Box-folder 2, Folder 52)
  - Marantz, Ray, 1977 (Box-folder 2, Folder 53)
  - Martin, Fredericka, 1970-1972; 1976 (Box-folder 2, Folder 54)
  - Mates, Dave, 1975 (Box-folder 2, Folder 55)
  - Nelson, Steve, 1977-1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 56)
  - Nicaragua, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 2, Folder 57)
  - Notes: Archives, undated (Box-folder 2, Folder 58)
  - Notes: International Brigades, 1987 (Box-folder 2, Folder 59)
  - Notes (Handwritten): “Spain Revisited”, 1982 (Box-folder 2, Folder 60)
  - Norris, Len, 1977-1978; 1985 (Box-folder 2, Folder 61)
  - Ornitz, Lou, 1981 (Box-folder 2, Folder 62)
  - Osipenko, A.S., 1983 (Box-folder 2, Folder 63)
  - Persoff, Jim, 1979 (Box-folder 2, Folder 64)
  - Pike, William, 1973; 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2, Folder 65)
  - Postcards (Blank), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Renn, Konrad, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ross, Adolph, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Salzman, Salman, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - San Francisco Bay Area Longshoremen’s Memorial Association, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Schwartz, George, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sills, Sam, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Smith, Randall “Pete”, 1977-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Spain: Carrillo Visit to Yale, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Spain: Politics, Prisoners, etc., 1962-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Spanish Civil War Historical Society, 1975; 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Steck, Bob, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sweden: Mayday Celebration, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Thornton, Phyllis, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tribute to Walter Schuetrum by his Daughter, Nancy Fontana (From The Volunteer, Vol.III, 2), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Troxel, Steve: Tribute Written by Walter Schuetrum, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, Undated; 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - US Army: Honorable Discharge, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - US Army: Separation Qualification Record, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - US Coast Guard: Certificate of Discharge, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Anniversaries, Bay Area, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - VALB: Bay Area Post, 1973-1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - VALB: Coverage in Bay Area Press, 1971-1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - VALB: Draft Constitution, Discussion, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - VALB: Draft Report, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - VALB: Finances, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - VALB: “Freedom Picnic”, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - VALB: Historical Commission, 1977; 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - VALB: Mailings, 1973-1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - VALB: Membership Books/Cards, 1938-1950 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - VALB: Minutes, Bay Area Post, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - VALB: Minutes, National Board, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - VALB: National Conferences (Reports, Discussions, etc.), 1973-1979 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - VALB: News, Notes on Vets, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - VALB: Subversive Activities Control Board (SACB), 1965 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Volunteer, The: WS Letter Commenting on Landis-Peet Exchange, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Wachtel, Marion (Merriman), 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Wallach, Hy: Notes on Conversation with, [1977] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wolff, Frieda, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Wolff, Milton, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Wyden, Peter, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Yates, James, 1980; 1985; 1986 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Series III: Artifacts and Memorabilia, 1937, undated., 1 box
  - Brigades Internacionales: Patches (2), undated (Box 4, Object 1)
  - Package of Gauze from the Swiss Army (“Individ Verbandpackchen der schwizerischen Armee”), 1937 (Box 4, Object 2)
  - Shrapnel from Explosive, Wrapped in Gauze, undated (Box 4, Object 3)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Pennant, undated (Box 4, Object 4)
  - Voluntarios Internacionales de la Libertad: Plaque, undated (Box 4, Object 5)